בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today is דף כ. Daf Kaf. We're starting
a little bit behind, we're starting from the משנה Mishnah on י"ט
עמוד ב. Yud Tet Amud Bet. We are dealing with תמורה Temurah
and ולדות vladot of different animals. We've already seen the זבח תודה.
zevach todah. By שלמים shelamim is that it follows the same הלכה
halacha as the animal itself. By תודה todah it's slightly different, you
don't bring the לחם. lechem. And by the, and by the עולה,
olah, the only issue is that you don't really have a ולד
vlad of an עולה, olah, so we dealt with the ולד vlad
of a תמורה temurah of an עולה, olah, and we saw the
discussion about and the debate about whether that actually would be brought
if it's a male, does it go by the original one or
should it not be brought, or do we say that as soon
as you hit a male that you actually can bring it? So,
or actually I correct, I change that. If it's a male עולה
olah and then a ולד vlad of its תמורה, temurah, then the
original one could be brought and then does the next male brought?
If you're מקדיש makdish a female עולה, olah, then it might be
different because then the one that originated it could not itself be
brought. So anyway, those were the questions about a ולד vlad of
an עולה olah where an עולה olah itself cannot directly have a
child, what is the story about the ולד? vlad?
Now we get, now we are looking at the issue about an
אשם asham and we talk about a female אשם. asham.
And here interestingly we see what do you do with a female
אשם? asham? You wait until it gets a מום mum and you
redeem it. This is because it's not one of those חמישה אשמות
chamisha ashamot like the five חטאות chataot that have to transform, a
חטאת מתה chatat metah and אשם asham becomes an עולה, olah, it
just can't be brought because it's a female, it's the wrong gender.
So you wait until it gets a מום mum and then you
transfer the money to another אשם. asham. And here interestingly we have
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that seems to treat the
wrong gender as a מום mum and says that you can redeem
it even without a מום. mum. So now we pick up with
that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look. It says, it
says like this: ולמה לי תסתאב? V'lama li tista'ev?
Why according to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the גמרא Gemara takes
it almost for granted רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. So why according
to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma with this female אשם asham do
you need for it to wait to get a blemish? תימכר, Timacher,
why don't, why don't we just sell it, meaning redeem it? כיון
דלא חזי למיאתי היינו מום, Kivan d'lo chazi l'miti haynu mum, that
the fact that you can't use it should be considered essentially like
a מום. mum. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav, היינו טעם, haynu ta'am, this is the reason.
Now the reason might even be a little bit sharper because remember
when you originally sanctified it, it never was fit for the use.
So it's not, there are some things that you can't bring that
aren't a מום, mum, like a טריפה. treifah. So you could have
sanctified it and it became a טריפה. treifah. Then you could have
asked, okay, I can't bring it but it's not a מום, mum,
is that enough to redeem it for? Here the question seems to
be, I think it's a little
sharper, not just that
you can't, that you can't bring it, but that even from the
very beginning it couldn't be brought and it should never have gotten
קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. So
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, היינו טעם, haynu ta'am, this
is the
reason, דאמרינן מיגו דנחית ליה קדושת דמים נחית נמי קדושת הגוף. d'amrinan
migu d'nachit lei kedushat damim nachit nami kedushat haguf.
And you can see that by the גמרא's Gemara answer, the גמרא
Gemara takes for granted that because it could not be brought, the
basic קדושה kedusha that should have taken place on it is a
קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, not a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. קדושת דמים
Kedushat damim again meaning you would use the proceeds but not that
the thing itself could be brought. So okay, if it can't be
said it's only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, how does it become, why
do you need a מום? mum? So the answer is, ah, but
although it starts with a קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, then it transforms
into קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, which is a really a little bit
like begging the question. You know, because we don't say that if
you sanctify something with a מום, mum, you sanctify something with a
מום mum or if you sanctify, well, טריפה treifah might be the
same as this, so we don't know. So you sanctify something, let's
say you sanctify a piece of wood or a car, we say
it's קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. Here, why do we say that it
becomes, it gets upgraded into a קדושת הגוף? kedushat haguf? Presumably because,
well, it's the right animal, it doesn't have a מום, mum, so
that should be enough to upgrade it to קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf.
Okay, but then that begs the question, why are we treating the
wrong gender different than the case of a מום? mum? So really
a little bit, it really does, the question really remains a little
bit unanswered. There's an implicit understanding that you're right, this is somehow
not as bad as a מום. mum. A מום mum automatically the
תורה Torah says you can redeem it, so therefore when you sanctify
it with a מום, mum, it never gets to קדושת הגוף. kedushat
haguf. Since this can't be, you know, but it sort of begs
the question because the whole question is like, well, why can't it
be redeemed in this state? But anyway, it's so, so if you
hear me struggling, it's because the גמרא Gemara really, it's a little
circular. Anyway, so that's the answer. The answer is, you're right, and
it's not really a full קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf because if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says נחית ליה נמי קדושת הגוף
למילתא דבעי מום, nachit lei nami kedushat haguf l'milsa d'ba'ei mum,
to the extent that you can't redeem it without a מום, mum,
not to the extent you could actually be מקריב makriv it. Okay,
so the answer is we don't know. I mean, that's not really
what the גמרא Gemara says, that's what I'm saying. Anyway, fine. So
the answer is, you're right, it's close enough that it's, although it's
קדושת דמים kedushat damim because it can't be brought, because it's close
enough, it transforms into קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. קדושת הגוף. kdushat haguf.
But because it's not a מום, mum, you can't redeem it without
a מום. mum. All right. So the גמרא's gemara answer, so the
funny thing is besides that being as I said a little bit
a little circular, the גמרא gemara actually infers something from here which
seems to be a little bit of a jump. So the גמרא
gemara says like this:
אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, זאת אומרת zos omeres המקדיש
זכר לדמיו hamakdish zachar lidamav קדוש קדושת הגוף. kadosh kdushat haguf. We've
had this statement before, comes up a lot. If somebody is מקדיש
makdish a male, the right animal, of the right gender, a male
animal for an אשם asham or a male animal for an עולה,
olah, okay, but you do it, you don't say I'm going to
bring I'm going to be turning this into an אשם asham or
an עולה. olah. You say I'm sanctifying this so that the proceeds
should be used to buy an אשם asham or an עולה. olah.
So that's crazy. Why should I sell this and use the proceeds
to buy an אשם asham or an עולה olah if the same
thing itself can be an אשם asham or an עולה? olah? So
there it automatically gets transferred, it automatically gets upgraded because that's where
the קדושה's kdusha heading anyway. Now that sentence in itself makes an
enormous amount of sense. If you're sanctifying it to use the proceeds
for this, why don't we just say that it automatically, you know,
transforms into that? Unless he's sanctifying it for the proceeds for
two of them, in which case it
might be a little bit better. Fine, I don't know, we're not
talking about that. Anyway, so that statement in itself makes sense. The
problem is how do you get it, זאת אומרת, zos omeres, how
do you get it from the previous statement? Because the previous statement,
the thing, you know, it never got upgraded to the point of
being able to be brought, and the thing itself couldn't be brought.
So again, it's קדושת דמים kdushat damim that transforms into קדושת הגוף.
kdushat haguf.
I understand, but there was the but there's the difference, there's a
logical jump, okay, because there the קדושת הגוף kdushat haguf didn't let
it be brought and the whole question was why actually does it
transform in that case since it can't be brought? And here it's,
you know, so here it makes a lot more sense than the
previous statement. All right, so now the גמרא gemara goes on. איתמר,
Itmar, we'll start. המקדיש זכר לדמיו. Hamakdish zachar lidamav. Now we actually
see this is a debate. רב כהנא אמר קדוש קדושת הגוף, Rav
Kahana amar kadosh kdushat haguf, רבא אמר אינו קדוש קדושת הגוף. Rava
amar eino kadosh kdushat haguf. So there was actually a debate whether
it transforms. והדר ביה רבא לגבי דרב כהנא מדרב יהודה אמר רב.
V'hadar bei Rava legabei d'Rav Kahana mi'd'Rav Yehuda amar Rav. And
רבא Rava in the end wound up conceding to רב כהנא Rav
Kahana based on this same thing of רב יהודה אמר רב Rav
Yehuda amar Rav that it does upgrade. So again, if you try
to sanctify something קדושת דמים kdushat damim and it's fit to be
קדושת הגוף, kdushat haguf, like the case about a male
that you only want to use the proceeds, so there we understand
why it should automatically upgrade. That makes intrinsic sense. The basic question
about why when you sanctify a wrong-gendered animal it has קדושת הגוף
kdushat haguf
really is a question that has not really, you know, been satisfactorily
answered. The גמרא gemara just says, yeah, that's what happens. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara goes on. רבי שמעון אומר כי מחסר שלא
במום. Rabbi Shimon omer ki mechasar shelo b'mum. Now רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says, no, this thing
counts as a מום mum and essentially it can't be brought and
it could be sold without a מום. mum. אמר ליה רבי חייא
בר אבין לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Chiya bar Avin l'Rabbi Yochanan,
מיגו דנחתא ליה קדושת דמים נחתא ליה נמי קדושת הגוף. migo d'necheta
lei kdushat damim necheta lei nami kdushat haguf. So now the גמרא
gemara has taken this so much for granted that now it reverses
itself and doesn't understand רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. I don't get it.
How can he say you can just redeem it without a מום?
mum? Now presumably you can conceptualize that in two ways, and this
is what I said before. You can either conceptualize it as the
wrong gender is a מום. mum. It doesn't seem that that's the
way the גמרא's gemara conceptualizing it. The גמרא gemara seems to be
saying since it can't be brought, so it's like sanctifying an something
that cannot be brought as a קרבן. korban. So if I sanctify
my car as an עולה, olah, it's only it doesn't get קדושת
הגוף. kdushat haguf. If I sanctify a wrong-gendered thing, it's like sanctifying
my car. So it's not because it's a מום mum that it
lets me redeem it, it's because it's the wrong thing and therefore
the only קדושה kdusha it gets is קדושת דמים, kdushat damim, which
is how come the גמרא gemara before פרינד freined it as, oh,
but then it transforms. It never explained why it transformed, but at
least anyway in the גמרא's gemara mindset רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
not saying it's a מום, mum, he's saying that it never got
קדושת הגוף, kdushat haguf, it was the wrong thing.
Which it did get קדושת דמים kdushat damim though, you just said
it's המקדיש. hamakdish.
I understand, but I'm telling you how the גמרא gemara is implicitly
understanding it.
Yeah, well it makes
that kind of sheds light on how you could consider the wrong
sex a מום mum because it's not a מום, mum, there's nothing
wrong with it.
That's what I'm exactly I'm saying, that even within רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that says you don't need a מום, mum, the גמרא's gemara
understanding not because he considers it a מום, mum, it's saying it's
the wrong thing, the wrong thing, it never got קדושת הגוף, kdushat
haguf, right, which is why when the גמרא gemara then challenges רבי
שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Like a car, you know, it's like on one perspective
you say like car, but it's not a car, it's an animal,
right. Exactly, yeah.
Would he say the same thing if it's a
male, if it was a male קרבן korban and a male was
offered, it would be the same thing?
Yes, presumably it was a male חטאת, chatas, presumably he'd say the
exact same thing. It's the wrong gender, it's not a preference for
like male over female or female or something like that. Okay, so
now which is why the גמרא's gemara question is, I don't get
it, if his whole point is that it only gets קדושת דמים
kdushat damim because it's not the right thing, why don't we have
an automatic upgrade? But again, the idea of automatic upgrade was never
fully explained before. You don't automatically upgrade it if you're מקדיש makdish
your car. So if you're מקדיש makdish this, why do you automatically
upgrade? So the גמרא gemara says, so אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back, רבי שמעון לטעמיה, Rabbi Shimon l'taamei, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
goes according to his reasoning, דאמר כל מידי דלא חזי לגופיה לא
נחית ליה קדושת הגוף. d'amar kol midi d'la chazi l'gufeh lo nechis
lei kdushat haguf. If you can't bring it itself, it doesn't get
upgraded into a קדושת הגוף. kdushat haguf. דתניא, D'tanya, and here's another
example of that. אשם בן שנה והביאו בן שתים. Asham ben shana
v'hevio ben shtayim. You're supposed some אשמות ashamos are one year old,
some are two years old, depending on which type of an אשם
asham it is, for which חטא. cheit. So... if it was supposed
to be a one year old and you sanctified a two year
old, בן שתים והביאו בן שנה, ben shtayim vehevio ben shana, or
if it was supposed to be two years old and you sanctified
a one year old, so there again, it's not actually a gender
issue, it's the wrong thing, it's not a מום, mum, but it's
not gender, it's not a מום, mum, it's just the wrong thing.
Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? כשרה ולא עלו לבעלים לשום חובה.
keshera velo alu lebaalim leshum chova.
It has קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf because it still has קדושת אשם,
kedushas asham, it's just not the אשם asham you need, but it's
a different אשם, asham, okay, because there are one year and two
year אשמות, ashamot, just not the one you need. So bring it,
but doesn't count for your obligation.
What if I had another one, a two year old, and I
need to use it for that one?
Presumably, that's what כשרה keshera means. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer,
although that depends on whether you know the specific חטא cheit in
mind, but presumably, anyway, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, presumably yes,
because you can't bring an אשם asham without a חובה. chova. Okay,
anyway, so רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, כל עצמן אינן קדושין.
kol atzman einan kedoshin. They're fundamentally not קדוש. kadosh. That doesn't mean
not קדוש kadosh at all, but it means it's only קדושת דמים,
kedushas damim, it's not קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, and therefore you cannot
bring it as a קרבן korban because it wasn't fit for what
you sanctified it for, and you would sell it and you would
use the proceeds.
Doesn't רש"י Rashi say אינן קדושים כלל? einan kedoshim klal?
Yeah, but רש"י Rashi says,
but if you take on looking, the גמרא Gemara says later and
תוספות Tosafot makes it very clear, whatever, that we're talking about קדושת
הגוף, kedushas haguf, not קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. All right, anyway, so,
all right, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, so the point here
is that, that, what do you call it, that the, I have
to stop interrupting me every second. Okay, so the point here is
that, that here it's even better, here, I mean here it's even
closer to being the right thing, right? Here, there is such a
thing as an אשם asham two year old, there is such a
thing as an אשם asham one year old. It's ממש, mamash, it's
almost the, you know, the original position makes a lot of sense,
let it have קדושת אשם, kedushas asham, just not be the one
you want. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is actually saying no, if
it's not what you tried to sanctify it for, since you had
a specific type of an אשם asham in mind, and you were
obligated in this specific אשם, asham, then if it's somehow not the
object you need, it only gets קדושת דמים kedushas damim but it
doesn't get קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. So here, and ממש mamash it
could have really been, you know, it could have been a type
of an אשם, asham, nevertheless that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says,
it's not the object you need. And therefore, and you see here
all the more so, he's not framing it as a מום. mum.
Nobody would say two year old is a מום, mum, especially if
it could be used as a different type of a קרבן. korban.
So we're not framing it as a מום, mum, we're just saying
if it's not what you were trying to do, it's only קדושת
דמים, kedushas damim, not קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on and says like this: והרי מחוסר זמן דלא
חזי. veharei mechusar zman delo chazi. How about an animal that is
not yet eight days old, can't be brought as a קרבן, korban,
that's not fit? ואמר רבי שמעון דקדוש, veamar Rabbi Shimon dekadosh, and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says we know in another context, we're going
to say it in a minute, that he says it is sanctified.
The case is the, it's a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in another
context that says if you sanctify an animal that's less than eight
days old and you slaughtered it outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
you're חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, which you would not
say if it did not have קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban, you're only
חייב שחוטי חוץ chayav shechutei chutz for קדושת קרבן. kedushas korban. So
how is that different? So the גמרא Gemara says, שאני מחוסר זמן
דחזי למחר. shani mechusar zman dechazi lemachar. No, that's not completely out
of the category. That in a few days will be ready, it
will naturally become ready, and therefore it does get קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי אשם בן שתים והביאו בן שנה
דחזי לשנה. ee hachi asham ben shtayim vehevio ben shana dechazi leshana.
So okay, so if you sanctify a one year old animal and
you needed a two year old, it'll naturally become ready, so let
it have the קדושה kedusha there, it is in the category, it
will automatically become fit. Why does he consider it not fit? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון. ela hainu taama
deRabbi Shimon. All right, here's the reason of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
במחוסר זמן דיליף ליה מבכור. bimechusar zman dyalif lei mibechor. He has
a special פסוק. pasuk. דתניא רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי
שמעון, detanya Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, מחוסר זמן
נכנס לדיר להתעשר. mechusar zman nichnas ledir lehitaseir. You can include a
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman in your animals when you're counting מעשר בהמה.
maaser behema. Why? It might wind up being the tenth and you'll
sanctify it. And you can't, presumably, what about not being able to
sanctify something that's not yet fit? והרי הוא כבכור, vaharei hu kebechor,
it's just like a בכור. bechor. מה בכור קדוש לפני זמנו וקרב
לאחר זמנו, ma bechor kadosh lifnei zmano vekarev achar zmano, the same
way a בכור bechor is sanctified the moment it's born but can't
be brought under eight days, אף מחוסר זמן קדוש לפני זמנו וקרב
לאחר זמנו, af mechusar zman kadosh lifnei zmano vekarev achar zmano, the
same true is all animals can be sanctified before they are eight
days old. So it's a special exception by מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman.
But the basic point is, is that he says, and here it's
very important to emphasize that the גמרא Gemara never frames it as
the wrong gender is a מום. mum. גמרא Gemara frames it as,
okay, if it can't be brought, it should be קדושת דמים, kedushas
damim, not קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. And that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says, if it can't be brought, it's like sanctifying your car,
it's קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, you tried to sanctify your car for
an אשם, asham, but what it translates into is
the proceeds for an אשם. asham. Even in a case where ממש
mamash it's roughly in the category, two years old, one years old.
And the חכמים Chachamim say no, since it's not a מום mum
and since it starts with קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, it gets upgraded
to a קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Now again, we understand the upgrade
in a case where maybe two year old, one year old, where
such a type of קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf exists. We understand the
upgrade if you're trying to sanctify a male for, for דמים damim
for an עולה olah and it becomes גוף guf for עולה. olah.
What the גמרא Gemara said and never fully fleshed out is why
does it get automatically upgraded in a case of a, of a
wrong gender, where the thing itself could never be brought, what is
the logic there for the automatic upgrade? You would not say it
in other cases. So that's what I said, the first question the
גמרא Gemara asks at the outset, why they say that upgrade is
never fully explained, just saying that it does happen, but obviously it
only happens... of animals, it wouldn't happen with a car and it
wouldn't happen with a בעל מום. baal mum. Michael asks a good
question, would it happen with a טריפה? treifa? I don't know, it's
not a מום, mum, but it's not a, you know, but it
can't be brought. What, you know, when would you say this, when
wouldn't you say this, is not, is not clear. Okay, let's, yeah,
yes. So, but I should just mention possibly the reason wrong gender
would be better than something like a טריפה treifa is because presumably
that could be used for a different type of קרבן. korban. It's
not completely out of the category of קרבן. korban. Although I'd have
to think through the chart, is there certain gender, certain genders and
certain years that can't be used for other types of things? But
maybe that might be the reason why gender is considered more in
the category and allows for the automatic upgrade. You're saying just in
the way, since we see from רב שמעון Rav Shimon דמחוסר זמן
demechusar zman is, you know, gets some, some קדושה. kedusha. So therefore
when he says אין קדושה כל עיקר, ein kedusha kol ikar, we
really mean it, it means קדושה. kedusha. Yeah, I mean it's very
strange. I know the כל עיקר kol ikar is an, is understood,
but someone here said, one minute... Yeah, I mean it's, I mean
we're not saying it more, different than we said before, which is
that we just said that it's, let me take a look. I
mean I think there was a רש"י Rashi or תוספות Tosafot about
this.
I'm just trying to understand that רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, I understand, I understand. No, I think the כל עיקר, kol
ikar, although the phrase is, is strong, there, you know,
it's, one minute... All right, look,
you're right, the language sounds very strong, but consistent with the other
גמרא, Gemara, I think we just have to understand it. Like if
you look at the רש"י, Rashi, I guess look at the רש"י
Rashi on the משנה. Mishna. רש"י Rashi says דהואיל וכל חזי למילתא
מום גמור הוא זה. dehoil vechol chazi lemilsa mum gamur hu zeh.
Well, actually there רש"י Rashi does frame it as a מום, mum,
although my point was that that wasn't how the גמרא Gemara was
framing it. ולא קדיש קדושת הגוף. velo kadish kedushat haguf. וכי מחל
מיד ותבי בדמיה אשם. vechi mechal miyad vesavei bidmei asham. Okay,
so, you know, רש"י Rashi certainly emphasizes that's the case in the
משנה Mishna about רב שמעון Rav Shimon and presumably the גמרא's Gemara
not making yet another category for רב שמעון, Rav Shimon, although I
admit that the language is pretty strong. Okay, now we're going to
go on. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. המקדיש נקבה לעולתו. Hamakdish nekeiva le'olato.
So there we have, that was one fascinating debate of what happens
if something can't be brought but it's not a מום, mum, does
it get a type of a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf or not?
Now, המקדיש נקבה לעולתו. Hamakdish nekeiva le'olato. Now, for some reason, right,
why did we start this whole debate by a female אשם? asham?
We had just gone through שלמים, shelamim, תודה, toda, and עולה. ola.
Well, עולה ola you could have had a, שלמים shelamim you can't
have an interesting example because שלמים shelamim is male or female. So
you can't have the interesting example of wrong gender. But עולה ola
you can. עולה ola is male. So what about if it is
a male? Wouldn't we have the same issue? המקדיש נקבה לעולתו
לפסחו ולאשמו. Hamakdish nekeiva le'olato lepischo ule'ashamo. So you're sanctifying a נקבה
nekeiva either for your עולה ola or your פסח pesach or your
אשם. asham. So פסח pesach also has to be male and we
had a case yesterday of a female פסח. pesach. Okay, so here
you have it applying to the other cases of things that have
to be male. עושה תמורה. oseh tmura. So those get a קדושת
הגוף kedushat haguf like we said by אשם. asham. This is the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. And because it gets a קדושת הגוף, kedushat
haguf, you can make a תמורה. tmura. Again, remember you can make
a תמורה tmura even from a בעל מום. baal mum. So you
can make a תמורה tmura from these types of animals because they
have a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. And another way of saying it
is you have to wait for them to get a מום mum
before you can redeem them. רבי שמעון אומר לעולתו עושה תמורה לפסחו
ולאשמו אינו עושה תמורה. Rabbi Shimon omer le'olato oseh tmura lepischo ule'ashamo
eino oseh tmura.
Okay, for an עולה ola I agree with you it's a קדושת
גוף, kedushat guf, not for פסח pesach and אשם. asham. So we
already know his position by אשם, asham, it has to be male,
so this way it's not a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. פסח pesach
is the same. The question is going to be why he concedes
the case of עולה. ola. So we'll see. שאין לך דבר עושה
תמורה אלא הראוי להסתאב. she'ein lecha davar oseh tmura ela haraui lehistayev.
The only thing that can make a תמורה tmura is something that
you would need for it to wait, הראוי haraui means it grazes,
to get a מום. mum. Meaning the only thing that can make
a תמורה tmura is something that you would need for it to
wait to get a blemish to redeem. But I basically am of
the position that if you've got the wrong gender, you don't need
for it to have a blemish to redeem it. Why don't you
need for it to have a blemish? Because it's not קדושת הגוף,
kedushat haguf, it's only קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, it's only value, it's
not intrinsic קדושה. kedusha. So basically, I mean it's a little, again,
he's not trying to persuade חכמים, Chachamim, he's just explaining, right, his
own internal argument. Since I'm of the position that these things only
get a קדושת דמים, kedushat damim, therefore they can't make a תמורה
tmura because I'm also saying that you don't need a blemish to
redeem them. Okay, fine, that's all what we knew of him. Why
does he concede the case of עולה? ola? So let's take a
look. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, so now we have רבי Rabbi commenting.
איני רואה דבריו של רבי שמעון בפסח. eini ro'eh devarav shel Rabbi
Shimon bepesach. I don't agree with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when it
comes to פסח. pesach. Maybe I would agree with him on אשם,
asham, at least I see his point by אשם, asham, but I
don't agree by פסח. pesach. פסח pesach should get a קדושת הגוף.
kedushat haguf. Why? הואיל ומותר פסח קרב שלמים. hoil umotar pesach karev
shelamim. Because if you have leftover money for a פסח pesach or
if you left over from a פסח, pesach, right, you had a
substitute and then you found it, etc., you had a... so what
happens after פסח? pesach? It's brought as a שלמים. shelamim. We saw
that the other day. So since a פסח pesach can in some
times can, you know, sort of transform into a שלמים, shelamim, being
מקדיש makdish a נקבה nekeiva for a פסח pesach is not completely
a wrong category mistake. And since it's not a wrong category mistake,
it's not like being מקדיש makdish your car. Okay? And therefore, it
does get a קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. So רבי Rebbe is saying
even within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that when it's the wrong gender,
it's like a wrong category, like a car and it's not relevant,
that's not true by a פסח. Pesach. There a wrong gender is
a little bit relevant because a פסח Pesach can become a שלמים.
Shelamim. So female is a little relevant. Okay, so fine, that explains
the פסח. Pesach. Now we still have to deal with the עולה.
Olah. Why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself concede עולה? Olah? ולימא
אינה נראה דברי רבי שמעון באשם הואיל ומותר אשם קרב עולה. Veleima
eini nirei divrei Rabbi Shimon be'asham ho'il umosar asham karev olah. So
the גמרא Gemara is now exactly, it hasn't yet even explained why
עולה Olah is different, but for whatever reason, which we'll explain in
a minute why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon concedes עולה, Olah, so why
doesn't רבי Rebbe say אשם Asham also isn't out of the category
as a female? How come אשם Asham isn't out of the category
as a female? Because an אשם Asham when it for when it
can't be brought, right, like if it's the case of נתכפרו בעלה,
niskaper ba'ala, בעליו, ba'alav, באחר ba'acher and so on, when you have
one, a separate one you designated, you found the first one and
so on, what happens to an אשם? Asham? An אשם Asham under
some circumstances can transform into an עולה. Olah. So therefore, since רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is conceding עולה, Olah, although interestingly עולה Olah itself
has to be male, but we're going to find out in a
minute why he concedes the case of עולה, Olah, so why doesn't
רבי Rebbe also say even an אשם Asham a female isn't out
of the category? Because an אשם Asham can become an עולה Olah
and a female עולה Olah for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon somehow is
close enough. So therefore an אשם Asham is a potential עולה Olah
and therefore should also be close enough. So why doesn't he so
to question רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by an אשם Asham as well?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, רבי סבר לה כרבנן דאמרי מותרות
לנדבת ציבור אזלי. Rebbe savar lah keRabbanan de'amri mosros linedvas tzibur azli.
Remember when an אשם Asham becomes an עולה, Olah, how does what
type of an עולה Olah is it? Is it a communal עולה
Olah or a private עולה? Olah? So רבי Rebbe holds that when
an אשם Asham becomes an עולה, Olah, it becomes a communal עולה,
Olah, לנדבת ציבור, linedvas tzibur, and therefore what? A communal עולה Olah
is out of the category of
תמורה. temurah. ואין
תמורה בציבור, Ve'ein temurah betzibur, and therefore it is there's no such
תמורה, temurah, so therefore it's not close enough. Now again, we have
not yet explained why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon concedes עולה. Olah. We're
about to turn to that. Yeah, well the גמרא Gemara before contrasted
them and that's what we're going to get to right now. So
why does but but we'll see that in a minute, but accepting
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon concedes עולה, Olah, basically says פסח Pesach
and אשם Asham female is completely out of the category, no קדושת
הגוף. kedushas haguf. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says a female פסח Pesach
is not completely out of the category because a פסח Pesach can
become a שלמים Shelamim and female שלמים Shelamim are possible, so a
female פסח Pesach is relevant enough, קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. So the
גמרא Gemara says how about a female אשם? Asham? Why is that
relevant enough? Well, an אשם Asham can become an עולה Olah and
for whatever reason, we don't know why, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon concedes
עולה, Olah, but since he does concede עולה, Olah, so a female
אשם Asham is close to being a female עולה Olah and therefore
also should be קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. And the גמרא Gemara says
no, even if it were to be a female עולה, Olah, the
אשם Asham were to transform into an עולה, Olah, it would be
a type of an עולה Olah which would be out of the
category of תמורה. temurah. And since at least here the relevance is,
right, we're saying we're asking the question can it make a תמורה
temurah or not? Right, remember the way it was framed here was
not the question does it need a מום mum to redeem it?
That's one implication of קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. The way the question
was framed is can it make a תמורה? temurah? Okay, that's the
other implication of קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. So the point is there's
no way a female אשם Asham is going to be able to
make a תמורה. temurah. Why not? Because even if it's close to
being an עולה, Olah, that type of an עולה Olah is out
of the category of תמורה. temurah. So there's no way a female
אשם Asham would be able to do that. Okay, that's just why
רבי Rebbe focused on פסח Pesach not אשם. Asham. But now we
get back to the unanswered question. Why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
concede עולה? Olah? Right, why is a female עולה Olah close enough
to have the קדושת הגוף? kedushas haguf? So let's take a look.
קסלקא דעתך, Kasalka dachach, so the גמרא Gemara is now saying we
are under the assumption
היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון hainu ta'ama deRabbi Shimon גבי מפריש נקבה לעולתו
gabei mafrish nekeva le'olaso why he concedes the case of עולה, Olah,
why a female עולה Olah does have קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, משום
הכי עושה תמורה, mishum hachi osa temurah, here's why it does a
תמורה, temurah, דהא איכא שם עולה עליה גבי עולת העוף. deha ika
shem olah aleiah gabei olas ha'of. Okay, this רש"י Rashi was quoting
this all of yesterday's דף daf but I bracketed it because anyway
תוספות Tosafos said it wasn't consistent with the גמרא Gemara there. But
anyway the גמרא Gemara here says why is a female עולה Olah
not consistent completely out of the category? Because there is such a
thing as a female עולה. Olah. What type of female עולה Olah
exists? Of a bird
עולה. Olah. Birds, the גמרא Gemara says תמות וזכרות בבהמה ואין תמות
וזכרות בעוף. tamus vezachrus bebehema ve'ein tamus vezachrus be'of. Okay, meaning that
the need for it to be a particular gender, male let's say
by an עולה, Olah, and the need for it to be unblemished
is only by animals. By birds, gender never matters and not only
that, even blemishes don't matter. The only thing that matters by birds
if it's missing a limb. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ah,
so the reason now you can't have a bird אשם Asham and
you can't have a bird פסח, Pesach, so that's not going to
help you. But you can have a bird עולה Olah and therefore
a female עולה, Olah, that concept is close enough that there he
would admit it's not completely irrelevant and it does get a קדושת
הגוף. kedushas haguf. Okay, so that's his
reasoning. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, says
the גמרא, Gemara, but if that's true, then there should be other
cases where the gender is close enough and and should also get
a קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. What
are the cases? בכהן גדול שהפריש נקבה... BeKohen Gadol shehifrish nekeva... פר
לפרו. par l'paro. So
a כהן גדול kohen gadol has to bring a פר, par, a
פר, par, you know, a cow on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
A bull, I should say, on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, for his
personal קרבן, korban, for the עבודה avoda of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
and instead he brings a פרה, para, a cow. So he gets
the wrong gender. So according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he should
concede that case, תקדש, tikadesh, why? דאיכא פרת חטאת, de'ika parat chatat,
because there's a פרה אדומה, para aduma, which is female. So the
גמרא Gemara says that's close enough, there's such a thing as a
female פרת חטאת. parat chatat. So he brought a male, he was
supposed to bring a male for his חטאת, chatat, but there is
such a thing as a female by פרה אדומה. para aduma. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, that's קדשי בדק הבית שיהו. kodshei bedek
habayit shehu. פרה אדומה, para aduma, although it's quasi like a קרבן,
korban, but you bring it outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and
they slaughter it out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and the
גמרא Gemara says that its basic status is בדק הבית, bedek habayit,
not literal בדק הבית bedek habayit like you're buying a vessel for
the temple, but it means it's not a קרבן korban type of
a קדושה. kedusha. And therefore it's not relevant to the world of
קרבנות. korbanot. וקדשי בדק הבית לא עבדי תמורה, ve'kodshei bedek habayit lo
avdi tmura, and therefore it's out of the category of תמורה, tmura,
and the whole point here, one of the things we're emphasizing is
the ability for a קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf for the sake of
תמורה. tmura. So here you can't say, oh, a male, a female
פרת חטאת parat chatat is close enough because there's a פרה אדומה.
para aduma. פרה אדומה para aduma isn't relevant. Of course, תוספות Tosafot
asks the question, there are tons of female פרת חטאת, parat chatat,
right? So why do we have to all of a sudden run
to the פרה אדומה para aduma case? So תוספות's Tosafot answer basically
is that what we're looking here for is something that is sort
of relevant for this person in particular, not just generically relevant. Okay,
now that's really not still so... so yes, are there... so why
פרה אדומה para aduma for כהן גדול? kohen gadol? It's not so
clear. I mean, it does say אלעזר Elazar is the אמור בפרשה
emor b'parsha but not אהרן. Aharon. So you don't need, you know,
there's never an idea of... so תוספות Tosafot really doesn't have a
fully satisfying answer why the גמרא's Gemara hyper-focused on פרה אדומה. para
aduma. But the real point that תוספות Tosafot says is that the
גמרא Gemara is more interested is like in your context, you particularly
in your context, could you theoretically have used a female instead of
a male? So by an עולה, ola, as we're going to see,
instead of bringing a she-pole, I could have brought a bird עולה.
ola. So I could have done that instead. Female was not irrelevant.
So again, it doesn't exactly explain why the גמרא Gemara had פרה
אדומה, para aduma, because that's also not relevant to the עבודה avoda
you're doing on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
On the other hand, maybe he's just metaher himself with the אפר
efer of the פרה אדומה para aduma before he starts?
Maybe. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot doesn't really have a fully satisfying answer to
that. Yeah, okay, anyway, right, it wasn't אדומה, aduma, it had to
be אדומה. aduma. Okay, anyway, yes.
So what I find interesting about this is that, you know, at
least by the עולה ola case, it was the same מין min
of קרבן, korban, right? Right. And here we're saying is פר, par,
oh wait, this פר par was for חטאת, chatat, right?
Yeah, yeah, פר par יום כיפור Yom Kippur was for חטאת. chatat.
Which פרות parot are for חטאת, chatat, by the way, Dov, בעל
קורא? balkorei? I mean, the standard מוסף musaf is a שעיר לחטאת,
se'ir l'chatat, right? What type of a standard individual brings a כבש
keves or שעירה? se'ira? What type of... are there... what do we
say, פר בן בקר תקח לחטאת, par ben bakar tikach l'chatat, that's
a פר. par. Where's your פרה? para?
בחנוכת המשכן? b'chanukat hamishkan? What? בחנוכת המשכן.
b'chanukat hamishkan. You're stuck on the מלואים. miluim. I mean, תוספות Tosafot
said, I didn't have a chance to check it, and I must
admit I don't know off the top of my
head. תוספות Tosafot says, רוב חטאות המזבח נקבות. rov chatot hamizbe'ach nekeivot.
Oh, that's true, right? Because no, because for individual, individual חטאות chatot
are female.
Okay, so but not פרות.
parot. So anyway, it seems clear the גמרא Gemara wanted to not
just be a... you could use... that there's such a thing as
a female in this category of חטאת, chatat, it wants it to
be the same type of an animal. But of course, that sort
of raises the question, but when you shift and say a bird
could be a female, you're also shifting the type of animal. Okay,
so I'm sorry, I re-read תוספות's Tosafot question is not that there
are female cows for חטאת. chatat. That I don't think we find.
But what it does... what you do find is plenty of female
sheep and goats, all the individual חטאות chatot are there. Right, so
if the גמרא's Gemara saying, oh, you could bring a bird and
that could be a female, so this כהן גדול kohen gadol also,
there's other חטאות, chatot, you know, same type of question. Anyway, so
the answer is that the גמרא Gemara to some degree wants it
to be roughly in the same category. All right, so that's the
question about the פר. par. So now the גמרא Gemara goes on
to say the following. אי הכי, ei hachi, אפילי שעיר לשעירתו, afilu
se'ir l'se'irato, let's say an individual is supposed to bring a שעירה
se'ira and instead he brings a שעיר. se'ir. Okay, there you go,
Rivka, that's the reverse case. Okay, male when it was supposed to
be female. תקדש, tikadesh, according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, let it
be קדוש. kadosh. Why? Isn't male irrelevant? No, דאיכא שעיר נשיא, de'ika
se'ir nasi, because if a person was a נשיא, nasi, a king,
and you had a sin, and you had to bring a חטאת,
chatat, it would be a male. So therefore a male for you
is not irrelevant. אינמי, inami, נשיא שהביא שעירה לשעירו, nasi she'heivi se'ira
l'se'iro, or if it's a נשיא nasi that designated a female instead
of... is male, תקדש tikadesh according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon should
be sanctified, דיחיד מפריש שעירה deyachid mafrish se'irah because as an individual
you as a lay person you would bring a female, so get
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if once you say oh, there
are sometimes under some circumstances you bring the other gender, and that
okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Anyway, so
therefore and that that's enough to give it קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf
here too. Sometimes a חטאת chatas can be of the other gender.
So the גמרא Gemara says הני תרי גופי נינהו. hani trei gufei
ninhu. No, those are different people. There's a lay person and a
king. Okay, as opposed to an any lay person can bring either
a sheep for an עולה olah or a bird for an עולה.
olah. So both of those are relevant to me. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says חטאו עד שלא נתמנו, chatu ad shelo nisnamnu, okay,
but let's say let's say the נשיא nasi sinned before he was
elected as a king. Or נתמנה. nisnamneh. כי מפריש שעיר לשעירתה יא
נתמנה. ki mafrish se'ir l'se'iratah ya nitmaneh. כי מפריש שעיר לשעירתה תקדש.
ki mafrish se'ir l'se'iratah tikdash. So there now that he is king,
he has to bring a female goat for the sin he did
as a commoner, but let's say in accidentally he designated out a
male goat. That's not completely irrelevant to him, because now he is
king. So now if he had to sin he would bring a
male. דאילו חטא חטא השתא בר שעיר הוא de'ilu chat cheit hashta
bar se'ir hu because now if he were to sin he would
bring a male goat. The גמרא Gemara says no, הא לא חטא
לא חייב בשעיר. ha lo cheit lo chayav b'se'ir. He hasn't sinned
yet. He hasn't sinned as a נשיא. nasi. Meaning yeah, but as
for his sin as a commoner, a male goat is irrelevant. Only
for his sin as a נשיא nasi would a male goat be
relevant. So what the גמרא Gemara is doing is it's narrowing what
it means that we should look at something an alternative model and
say it's close enough. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to
say so how do you get close enough by the עולה? olah?
But basically it starts by saying if I'm bringing an עולה, olah,
a sheep, in theory I could have brought a a bird. And
a bird gender wouldn't matter. So therefore when I sanctify my sheep,
even if it's the wrong gender according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
it's close enough. So the גמרא Gemara says oh, let's look there
at other cases that you say in theory it could have been
something similar and therefore and maybe it should be קדוש kadosh even
though it's the wrong gender. So first it looks about the sort
of the פר par of a חטאת, chatas, how about a פר
חטאת? par chatas? And again תוספות Tosafos points out there again for
some reason the גמרא Gemara is sort of sticking to the same
animal. So the only other פרה parah that's a חטאת chatas is
פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So the גמרא Gemara says that's really not
so relevant. It doesn't have קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Again there sort
of the similarity is not as we pointed out, not that the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring a פרה אדומה parah adumah for
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but at least the similarity is it's a
cow and a חטאת. chatas. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
okay, but how about a sin offering, a שעיר se'ir and a
שעירה se'irah under different circumstances, you know I could bring one or
the other. The גמרא Gemara says yeah, but you'll never as you
who you are and your current status, you're never going to be
able to bring either. Okay, so what the גמרא Gemara is narrowing
it and saying what we are looking for according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon where he's willing to concede if somebody that in your
status could be bringing this thing as an alternative. Only in those
cases do we say that therefore in that case the wrong gender
would be close enough. So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי הכא נמי הא לאו עולת עוף קמייתי? ei
hachi hacha nami ha lav olas of kamaisi? So here too you're
not bringing an עולת עוף, olas of, you're happen to be you're
bringing a sheep or goat or whatever you're bringing and presumably what
the גמרא Gemara is assuming is that if you are a you
know person of means and you just obligate yourself in an עולה,
olah, you're not entitled to bring an עולת העוף. olas ha'of. I
mean the תורה Torah in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra says if
you're bringing an עולה, olah, so אם כשב הוא מביא, im kesev
hu mavia, you know if you bring it as a כשב, keves,
if you bring it as a as a שעיר, se'ir, whatever and
then finally it says you know ואם העוף, ve'im ha'of, I forget
exactly but whatever. Then it introduces here thank you very much. So
the way the תורה Torah opens up ויקרא, Vayikra, ממש mamash the
first thing in ויקרא Vayikra is עולה, olah, right? And it starts
by saying right, אם עולה קרבנו מן הבקר זכר תמים יקריבנו, im
olah korbano min habakar zachar tamim yakrivenu, then it says ואם מן
הצאן קרבנו מן הכשבים ומן העזים לעולה, ve'im min hatzon korbano min
hakesavim u'min ha'izim l'olah, ואם מן העוף עולה קרבנו להשם. ve'im min
ha'of olah korbano l'Hashem. So it gives you a whole range, doesn't
tell you what's to determine which one, but presumably the גמרא Gemara
understands that if you're if you're a person of means, then if
you just obligate an עולה, olah, you're not entitled to bring something
cheap like a bird. So the גמרא Gemara says no, not necessarily,
maybe you are entitled. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי
שמעון סבר לה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Shimon savar lah k'Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah, he holds like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah, דתנן d'tnan הרי עלי עולה יביא כשב. harei alai olah
yavi keves. If somebody generically says I'm obligated an עולה, olah, you
bring a כשב, keves, a sheep, which is middle between the cow
and the bird. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר או תור או בני
יונה. Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer o tor o bnei yonah. If
you want you can go down to bringing even the pigeons and
the turtledoves, you can bring even the you know even birds. So
if you are even if you are a person of means, if
you obligate an עולה olah and if you're bringing an עולה, olah,
you know what? You could have brought a bird עולה olah as
well. That would have also been acceptable. And therefore because it's in
roughly the category of things that you're doing and the different gender
is relevant, so therefore it's enough for קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. I
want to say two things. First of all, רש"י Rashi before read
but I bracketed it out that the גמרא Gemara was thinking that
maybe we're talking about a very specific type of an עולה olah
which does have a slight The other thing is you actually see
from רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon before about the two-year-old and the one-year-old
that the idea that was within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to be
considered sort of relevant enough and close enough, it really has to
be for you and your circumstances. Because a two-year-old אשם asham or
a one-year-old אשם asham actually is really a קרבן, korban, just not
for you right now. And even for him though, because it's not
relevant for you and your circumstances, it doesn't get קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. So you really do understand that the גמרא gemara has to
say that when he's willing to concede that a wrong gender is
close enough, it really has to be not just generically such a
type of a thing could exist, but it has to be able
to exist for you. And therefore, because an עולה, olah, a bird
עולה olah is possibly relevant for you, even if you're a person
of means, because it's potentially relevant for you, then the wrong gender
is not completely out of the category. And the רבנן rabbanan would
say, I mean, because it would be as much a question on
them, no? No, the Rabbis say that it does... what do you
mean? It's a נקבה לעולה, nekevah la-olah, like we... no, the רבנן
rabbanan also say it's קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. He's conceding to the
רבנן. rabbanan. Right, exactly. So I'm saying all this is רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, but we'd say that, you know, we can also have
asked the same question to the Rabbis. Why is it קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf if it's the wrong gender? That's what we said from
the very beginning. And from again, it gets back to the point
that what we see according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is, just
to then pull it together where we are. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says if it's the wrong gender or if it's the wrong age
or whatever, if it's not relevant, then even if it's a nice-looking
בהמה, behemah, it's only קדושת דם kedushas dam and it's not קדושת
הגוף. kedushas haguf. The one case he'll concede is where the animal
is potentially... it's actually funny because a female sheep is not really
relevant, but the concept of a female עולה olah is close enough
for you and your category that he'll concede it's קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. The Rabbis say no, it always gets קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf.
Why? Isn't it irrelevant? So the גמרא gemara never fully explained it.
It said upgrade. And the best we could say is is that
maybe because all of these things, although you have to see if
it's always true, could be used as קרבנות korbanos elsewhere, right? A
female sheep could be used as a different type of a קרבן.
korban. A two-year-old could be used in a different type of a
קרבן. korban. It's not like it has a מום, mum, it's not
like it has טריפה. treifah. And maybe therefore that's with enough within
the category of קרבנות korbanos that it does get a type of
a קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. That's just our speculation, but I think
that's the closest we can get to understanding why it gets that
upgrade according to the רבנן. rabbanan. Okay, so let's take a look
now as the גמרא gemara continues. Okay, תנן התם. tnan hasam. We
taught over there. המקדיש נכסיו. hamakdish nechasav. This is over in, I
think where... in שקלים. shekalim. Right, it's in שקלים. shekalim. המקדיש נכסיו
והיו בהן בהמה ראויה לגבי מזבח. hamakdish nechasav vehayu bahen behemah reuyah
legabei mizbe'ach. Somebody says, "I sanctify all of my property to the
Temple." Okay, so normally we assume everything goes to the Temple treasury,
but some of his property had some nice animals that were unblemished.
Okay, והיו בהן בהמה ראויה לגבי מזבח. vehayu bahen behemah reuyah legabei
mizbe'ach. So what do you do with them? זכרים ונקבות, zcharim u-nekevot,
male and females. רבי אליעזר אומר זכרים ימכרו לצרכי עולות ונקבות ימכרו
לצרכי שלמים ודמיהם יפלו עם שאר נכסיו לבדק הבית. Rabbi Eliezer omer
zcharim yimachru l'tzorchei olot u-nekevot yimachru l'tzorchei shelamim u-dmeihem yiplu im shear
nechasav l'bedek habayit. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, "No, we assume
when you say I'm giving it all to the Temple, you mean
all in one category." So since for the house and the car
and everything else it means to the Temple treasury, your beautiful בהמות
behemot as well also go to the Temple treasury. The only thing
is that we have a principle that once an animal which is
fit for the מזבח mizbe'ach gets under the control of הקדש, hekdesh,
we have to make sure that it's going to get to the
altar. It's like inappropriate that it was so close to being a
קרבן korban and it's not going to end up as a קרבן.
korban. So the קדושה kedushah is not קדושת קרבן, kedushas korban, it's
קדושת בדק הבית, kedushas bedek habayit, it's Temple treasury, but there's a
principle that we want to make sure it gets onto the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So what do you do? You take your nice cows and
sheep or whatever, you sell them to people that need to bring
קרבנות, korbanot, okay? The proceeds go to the Temple treasury because these
were owned by the Temple treasury, but because they're being bought by
people that need to bring קרבנות, korbanot, they will get on the
מזבח mizbe'ach as well and that's idea of making sure they get
to the מזבח mizbe'ach is preserved. But their קדושה kedushah is קדושה
kedushah for the Temple treasury. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says.
So that's what it means לצרכי עולות לצרכי l'tzorchei olot l'tzorchei whatever,
you know, for... where was it? לצרכי עולות לצרכי שלמים. l'tzorchei olot
l'tzorchei shelamim. You sell it to people who need to bring an
עולה olah or שלמים, shelamim, they'll bring it, but this money ודמיהם
יפלו עם שאר נכסיו לבדק הבית, u-dmeihem yiplu im shear nechasav l'bedek
habayit, that goes to the Temple treasury. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua
omer, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, "No, when you have animals, the
קדושה kedushah is split." The implicit קדושה kedushah for the animals in
your household is קדושת קרבן. kedushas korban. That's always seen as a
higher use of something to actually use it as a קרבן. korban.
So זכרים הן, zcharim hen, and what type of a קרבן? korban?
We're going to assume it's a קרבן korban of an עולה. olah.
Why an עולה? olah? Well, you're not obligated in a חטאת. chatat.
The only other free will is a שלמים, shelamim, but a שלמים
shelamim you partake of most of the meat. So if you're giving
it over to the Temple, the thing that's most similar to a
complete gift to the Temple is an עולה. olah. So for your
animals, we would translate it as you were מקדיש makdish them as
עולות. olot. Okay, so זכרים עצמן יקרבו עולות. zcharim atzman yikrevu olot.
So the males you bring as עולות. olot. ונקבות, u-nekevot, and the
females, presumably we only apply this by the way to the תמימים.
tmimim. If it's a blemish, we assume that's just a straight gift
to the Temple. Okay, but again, by the females that are unblemished,
so that's... ימכרו לצורכי שלמים ויביא בדמיהם עולה, yimachru letzorchei shelamim veyavi
bidmeihem olah, ושאר נכסים יפלו לבדק הבית. usha'ar nechasim yiplu leBedek HaBayit.
So in those types of a things what do you do? So
you basically you sell them without a blemish, so here we're selling
female עולות olos without a blemish, right, and that's going to be
our question, but because they're females it we now are treating it
as if it's only קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, so therefore you sell
them without a blemish, you use the money and you get you
get win both ways. So rather than just saying I'm going to
redeem it on this money and use this money for an עולה,
olah, no, temple treasury now owns this, they want to make a
profit off of this, they don't want to use their own money,
so they'll sell it to somebody who needs to bring a שלמים,
shelamim, that's what you can do with a female, you bring a
שלמים, shelamim, that person buys it, that money now gets the קדושה
kedusha that was on this, which was קדושה kedusha to be used
for an עולה, olah, and the proceeds then are used to buy
an עולה. olah. So you both bring an עולה olah for this,
okay, but you don't have to use your own בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash money. They sell it to somebody, the money they got from
that person now gets the transfer קדושה, kedusha, is used to buy
an עולה, olah, and that person is now going to bring it
as a שלמים, shelamim, which is also good because it's the principle
that once it's under the control of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
we want to ensure that it gets to be brought as a
קרבן. korban. What's relevant for us is effectively it's like you were
מקדיש makdish a נקבה nekeivah for an עולה olah and we see
you're redeeming it without a מום. mum. And before we said that
even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agreed that you needed a מום mum
when it was מקדיש makdish a נקבה nekeivah for an עולה. olah.
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. So the גמרא
Gemara says: אמר ליה רבי חייא בר אבא לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba le-Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יהושע דאמר זכרים עצמן יקרבו
עולות, Rabbi Yehoshua de-amar zcharim atzman yikarvu olos, according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that says the males are עולות, olos, נקבות היכי מקריבין
שלמים? nekeivos heichi makrivin shelamim? How do you bring the females as
שלמים? shelamim? המכל מקום קדושה דחויה קאתיא. Ha mikol makom kedusha de-chuya
ka-asya. They're coming from a pushed off קדושה. kedusha. Now it doesn't
exactly clear what that sounds, it almost sounds like there's somehow like
it's like a נדחה nidcheh by the שלמים. shelamim. So the לשון
אחר, lashon acher, again we have the לשון אחר, lashon acher, makes
the question a lot clearer. So let's just read the לשון אחר.
lashon acher. אמר ליה רבי חייא בר אבא לרבי יוחנן, Amar lei
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba le-Rabbi Yochanan, מדקאמר רבי יהושע זכרים עצמן יקרבו
עולות, mi-de-ka-amar Rabbi Yehoshua zcharim atzman yikarvu olos, since he says the
males are themselves brought as an עולה, olah, למימר דקדושת הגוף אקדישינהו.
le-meimar de-kedushas ha-guf akdishinu. So we see that the קדושה kedusha he's
giving to the unblemished animals is a קדושת הגוף. kedushas ha-guf. אי
הכי נקבות אמאי ימכרו לצורכי שלמים? I hachi nekeivos amai yimachru le-tzorchei
shelamim? How can you straight away sell the females without a blemish
and then use the money for an עולה? olah? בעיא רעייה, ba'aya
re'iya, it needs to graze, it needs to get a מום. mum.
Even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that a female עולה olah needs
a מום. mum. So אמר ליה, amar lei, רבי יהושע סבר לה
כרבי שמעון Rabbi Yehoshua savar lei ke-Rabbi Shimon of our משנה mishna
by an אשם, asham, דאמר כל מידי דלא חזי ליה לגופיה לא
נחתי ליה קדושת הגוף, de-amar kol midi de-lo chazi lei le-gufei lo
nachsi lei kedushas ha-guf, that if it wasn't fit for the thing
itself, even if it doesn't have a מום, mum, it's only קדושת
דמים. kedushas damim. דתנן, de-nan, our משנה, mishna, רבי שמעון אומר תימכר
שלא במום. Rabbi Shimon omer timacher she-lo be-mum. So כיון דלא חזי
נקבה לאשם לא נחתי ליה קדושת הגוף. keivan de-lo chazi nekeivah le-asham
lo nachsi lei kedushas ha-guf. So because you can't use a נקבה
nekeivah for an אשם, asham, it doesn't have קדושת הגוף. kedushas ha-guf.
So basically what he's saying is עולה olah isn't special according to
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. We just got through the whole beginning of
the עמוד amud to say that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says עולה's
olah different because נקבה's nekeivah close enough. He says no, אשם asham
is special. Even for an עולה olah if it's a female it
doesn't it's only קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, not קדושת הגוף. kedushas ha-guf.
He rejects the ברייתא braisa that we quoted earlier. Okay and in
theory רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon could have said his position by the
previous משנה. mishna. One minute. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, אימא
דאמר רבי שמעון גבי נקבה לאשם דליכא שם אשם על אמה, eima
de-amar Rabbi Shimon gabei nekeivah le-asham de-leika shem asham al imah, where
does that true he says it by a female אשם asham that
the original, the mother, it's an interesting idea you're using the word
mother, that was exactly the phrase we used yesterday, but there we
were talking about children, here we're not talking about children. So anyway
it's a borrowed phrase. But it means there the thing itself was
never it's out completely out of the category of אשם. asham. And
therefore he says it's only קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. אבל גבי נקבה
לעולה דאיכא שם עולה על אמה, aval gabei nekeivah le-olah de-ika shem
olah al imah, but by נקבה nekeivah for an עולה olah where
again not really the mother but it means the thing itself is
not completely out of the category, why not completely out of the
category? Because as we said there's an עולת העוף olas ha-of which
is a נקבה. nekeivah. רבי שמעון מודה, Rabbi Shimon modeh, he should
agree conceptually. ועוד הא שמענא ליה לרבי שמעון לעולת העוף עושה תמורה.
ve-od ha shamina lei le-Rabbi Shimon le-olas ha-of oseh tmurah. We have
a ברייתא braisa explicitly, not only logically should רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
agree by an עולה, olah, but we've got a ברייתא braisa where
he agrees by an עולה olah that it's קדושת הגוף. kedushas ha-guf.
So he says, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him,
רבי יהושע סבר לה כאידך תנא אליבא דרבי שמעון. Rabbi Yehoshua savar
lei ke-idach tana aliba de-Rabbi Shimon. No, there's a debate of תנאים
Tannaim about רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position whether he would concede the
case of an עולה. olah. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braisa, רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Shimon, אף לעולה אינו עושה תמורה. af le-olah
eino oseh tmurah. There's a version of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
he doesn't concede an עולה, olah, even for an עולה olah it
doesn't make a תמורה, tmurah, it does not get a קדושת הגוף.
kedushas ha-guf. So what we have here is a very nice little,
I mean it's a nice you know little סוגיא, sugya, very compact
where it basically said you've got something that doesn't have a מום,
mum, isn't fit for being a קרבן, korban, but on the other
hand, you know maybe in theory could be used for a different
type of a קרבן. korban. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says once it's
not fit, even if it's not fit for you, I mean the
something like that, so you don't need a מום, mum, it's only
קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. And then the only question is would he
concede a case of a female עולה, olah, because there is a
concept of a female עולה. olah. And in theory you could buy
a totally different animal, but in theory at least there's that concept.
Okay, and that's the one question that's left debated whether he would
concede the case of a female עולה. olah. And the חכמים Chachamim
say that it does get a קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. Why is
it different than a מום? mum? Presumably we're speculating, but presumably because
at least it could be brought for a different type of a
קרבן. korban. Presumably the חכמים Chachamim would agree that if it were
of a טרפה, treifa, you know, that they are actually, although you
might need a מום mum to redeem it, but they are actually,
well actually no, not clear. Anyway, so it's unclear what the actually
חכמים Chachamim would say by a case of a טרפה, treifa, would
they there concede that it's completely irrelevant or not? But at least
in this case where it's just a question of gender or age,
that's not, that is enough for it to still get a קדושת
הגוף. kedushat haguf. Yes, Rabbi? So in your case of the נכסים
nechasim and you know you had the דמי dmei whatever he says
there, so most of the נקבות nekeivot were sold, you know, for
someone to make an עולה. olah. And again, why wouldn't they just
bring a שלמים? shelamim? Because I said, we assume that the thing
that the קדושת קרבן kedushat korban that's most similar to קדושת מזבח
kedushat mizbeach is an עולה, olah, it's a fully giving over to
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as opposed to a שלמים. shelamim. So
if we're going to translate your קדושה kedusha by the animals to
be a קדושת מזבח, kedushat mizbeach, עולה olah is the way we're
going to translate it. So then it's like מקדיש עולה. makdish olah.
Why wouldn't they have brought שלמים? shelamim? Because he could have said
מקדיש... makdish I understand, whatever, okay, but we don't. All right, let's
take a look now at the next משנה. Mishna. So that is
about a female אשם. asham. Now we're going to get moved on
to what was our focus, which is תמורה tmura and ולד. vlad.
So let's take a look. תמורת אשם, tmurat asham, let's say you
have a תמורה tmura of an אשם. asham. Right, now remember a
תמורת חטאת tmurat chatat is מתה, meita, so we know a תמורת
אשם tmurat asham has to graze and you redeem it and use
money for an עולה. olah. Or ולד תמורה, vlad tmura, or you
have the ולד vlad of the תמורה, tmura, if the תמורה tmura
was a female, right? Or you could have said if you were
מקדיש a נקבה nekeiva for an אשם, asham, which gets us back
to our previous משנה. Mishna Okay, but you have the child of
a תמורה, tmura, ולדן וולד ולדן עד סוף כל העולם. vladan u'vlad
vladan ad sof kol ha'olam. So what do you do? ירעו עד
שיסתאבו וימכרו ויפלו דמיהם לנדבה. yiru ad she'yista'avu v'yimachru v'yipelu dmeihem l'nedava.
So those cases you let them graze and you use the proceeds.
Why? Since the תמורה tmura already that's the הלכה, halacha, תמורת אשם
tmurat asham parallel to תמורת חטאת. tmurat chatat. תמורת חטאת tmurat chatat
you let die, תמורת אשם tmurat asham you let it graze, use
the money for an עולה. olah. So that's true by a תמורה,
tmura, so any children of that תמורה tmura would also graze and
you would use the money for an עולה. olah. וימכרו ויפלו דמיהם
לנדבה. v'yimachru v'yipelu dmeihem l'nedava. Now there the עולה olah there means
נדבה nedava means a נדבת ציבור, nedvat tzibur, communal עולה. olah. רבי
אליעזר אומר ימותו. Rebbe Eliezer omer yamutu. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says
they die because he says an אשם asham is like a חטאת
chatat and therefore by a חטאת chatat you have to let it
die, by an אשם asham you let it die. רבי אלעזר אומר,
Rebbe Elazar omer, רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar says, יביא בדמי עולות. yavi
bidmei olot. That it sounds like the idea of נדבה, nedava, the
משנה Mishna itself will reflect on that, but means a private עולה,
olah, not a communal עולה. olah. Now actually we're going to shift
gears. Until now this was just a debate about ולד vlad and
תמורה tmura and so on, but now actually we're going to expand
the discussion in general to all the אשמות ashamot that can't be
brought, that parallel the חטאות chataot that die. What about the אשמות,
ashamot, they don't die, what do you do with them? So again,
we know you use the money for an עולה, olah, but now
it's going to just broaden that discussion. אשם שמתו בעליו. asham she'meitu
ba'alav. So here are the other cases like a חטאת chatat that
you would in a חטאת chatat case you'd let it die. The
owners have died, so they don't need it anymore, it's no longer
relevant for sin. או שנתכפרו בעליו, o she'nitkapru ba'alav, or they were
atoned for by another animal. Okay, so in those types of a
case, and we already mentioned תמורה tmura and ולד, vlad, so which
are the basics, so which ones are we missing? ולד חטאת, vlad
chatat, תמורת חטאת, tmurat chatat, מתו בעליו, meitu ba'alav, נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru
b'acher, and עברה שנתה. avra shnata. Oh, so we didn't have the
one thing that it's too old. But okay, that's the fifth case.
Anyway, we had the first cases of תמורה tmura and ולד, vlad,
these are the other two cases of that they were atoned for
elsewhere, they died or they already had an atonement. So what's the
הלכה? halacha? By a חטאת chatat you let it die. Here the
הלכה halacha is ירעו עד שיסתאבו וימכרו ויפלו דמיהם לנדבה. yiru ad
she'yista'avu v'yimachru v'yipelu dmeihem l'nedava. Same thing we said before, wait for
blemish, use the money for a communal עולה. olah. רבי אליעזר אומר
ימותו. Rebbe Eliezer omer yamutu. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer again says they
die. רבי אלעזר אומר, Rebbe Elazar omer, רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar says,
יביא בדמי עולה. yavi bidmei olah. You bring an עולה. olah. So
now the whole difference between רבי אלעזר Rebbe Elazar and the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says נדבה, nedava,
he says עולה. olah. So the משנה Mishna says what's the, the
משנה Mishna itself asks, what's the difference? They're both saying bring an
עולה. olah. So the משנה Mishna, says, here's the difference. ומה בין
דברי רבי אלעזר לדברי חכמים? u'mah bein divrei Rebbe Elazar l'divrei Chachamim?
It's a very interesting משנה, Mishna so self-reflective. Right, so now when
you can't use this אשם, asham, besides the opinion that they die,
we have two other opinions. One is נדבה, nedava, which means an
עולה, olah, and the other is עולה. olah. So they're both saying
עולה, olah, what's the difference? So the משנה mishna says, here's the
difference. אלא בזמן שהיא באה עולה, ela bizman she'hi ba'ah olah, or
the side says חובה, chovah, meaning according to the opinion of רבי
אלעזר Rebbe Elazar that uses the phrase עולה, olah, means a private
עולה. olah. So what does it mean a private עולה? olah? So
if it's my personal עולה, olah, my אשם asham transformed into my
personal עולה, olah, סומך עליה, somech aleha, if it's my קרבן korban
I do סמיכה, smicha, ומביא נסכים, u'meivi nesachim, I have to bring
the נסכים, nesachim, the wine and the flour, ונסכים משלו, u'nesachim mishelo,
I have to pay for them because it's my קרבן korban so
I'm bringing the נסכים. nesachim. אם היה כהן, im haya kohen, if
I was a כהן kohen and I was bringing this, עבודתו ועורו
שלו, avodato ve'oro shelo, and when a כהן kohen brings his own
קרבן korban to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, even if it's not
his day, his week, he's entitled to bring his own קרבן, korban,
okay? Any כהן kohen that shows up, they can bring their קרבן
korban that day. And if I do the עבודה avoda that day,
I'm also entitled to keep the skin of the animal because an
עולה olah is all burnt, but the skin, which is leather, is
I get to keep. That if it's a private קרבן. korban. ובזמן
שנדבה, u'bizman she'nedava, however, according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that
uses the phrase נדבה, nedava, which means a communal עולה, olah, here's
the way communal is different. אינו סומך עליה, eino somech aleha, because
communal there's no סמיכה. smicha. סמיכה smicha is only by private קרבנות
korbanot by the owners, not by communal קרבנות. korbanot. ואינו מביא עליה
נסכים, ve'eino meivi aleha nesachim, I the person don't bring the נסכים.
nesachim. נסכים משל ציבור. nesachim mishel tzibur. Now that doesn't mean there
are no נסכים, nesachim, but it means that they're not I don't
have to pay for them, they're not my obligation, they're the they're
the ציבור's, tzibur they're the communal obligation. So the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash has to use its own funds for bringing the נסכים. nesachim.
And not only that, אף על פי שהוא כהן, af al pi
she'hu kohen, if I'm going to bring even if I'm a כהן,
kohen, עבודתו ועורו משל אנשי משמר, avodato ve'oro mishel anshei mishmar, I
don't have a right to do the עבודה, avoda, it's not my
personal קרבן, korban, the כהנים kohanim of that of that week get
to do it, they keep the skin, it's not my personal קרבן.
korban. So basically we have turned this from a discussion about תמורה
tmura and ולד, vlad, which has been our focus, to a general
discussion of what do you do with an אשם asham that gets
derailed, which is תמורה, tmura, ולד, vlad, נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru be'acher, מתו
בעליה, meisu ba'aleha, and there's a three-way debate. One person is one
position of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, whatever his die, which is sort
of like what's the same thing by חטאת. chatas. And then there's
two variations of an עולה, olah, communal and private עולה olah with
the differences that the משנה mishna mentioned, okay? And this is why
by the way we're going to start turning after we wrap up
the תמורה tmura and ולד vlad discussion, the next פרק perek is
going to turn to a whole focus on the one thing we've
been avoiding. Because the one thing we've been avoiding is the חטאת
chatas where the animal dies. Okay, and all the cases that the
animal dies for חטאת. chatas. So רבקה's Rivka going to really enjoy
her next פרק, perek, but anyway we're already hinting to it by
now we're talking about an אשם asham that gets derailed, not just
by תמורה tmura and ולד vlad and what happens to it. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. וצריכא. u'tzricha. Now here's a
very fascinating thing. Although רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says dies, and the
גמרא Gemara in in the beginning of זבחים, Zevachim, it's clear that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רש"י Rashi said this earlier is of
the opinion that the גמרא Gemara it's even the first משנה mishna,
in זבחים, Zevachim, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says אשם הרי הוא כחטאת,
asham harei hu ke'chatas, okay? An אשם asham has the same הלכות
halachos of a חטאת. chatas. So חטאת chatas dies and אשם asham
dies, it's for a fundamental identify identification of the two. The גמרא
Gemara here understands that he says it dies, it's more of like
a rabbinic concern and not fundamentally because we're defining an אשם asham
like a חטאת, chatas, okay? So first the גמרא Gemara focus on
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that frames it as a rabbinic concern. Let's
take a look. וצריכא, u'tzricha, you need to tell me in both
cases that it dies, both the תמורה tmura and ולד vlad case
and the case of where they were where the owners died or
they were atoned for elsewhere. דאי אשמיעינן אשם בהך אמר רבי אליעזר
ימותו משום דגזר אחר כפרה אטו לפני כפרה. de'i ashmi'inan asham behach
amar Rabbi Eliezer yamusu mishum degazar achar kapara atu lifnei kapara. If
it had just told me the cases of when they were atoned
for elsewhere and he said you have to let the animal die,
maybe there he's saying that the reason you have to let the
animal die is because if we let you bring the animal itself
if we let you, excuse me, redeem the money and use it
for an עולה, olah, then you're going to do it even after
you were atoned for, meaning here's the important point. In the first
case of the משנה, the animal that is being redeemed or dying
is not the original אשם. asham. I have my original אשם, asham,
I got my תמורה, tmura, the kids, etc. Those are one case
where he says these things rather than grazing says רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer have to die. Then the next case is when it's the
original case, because the owner died or the owner got another atonement
and the original אשם asham is going to have to either graze
or die. So he said well in that case where it's the
original אשם asham we could understand why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
die, because if we were to allow me to redeem it, even
the original אשם, asham, I might come to redeem it even if
the special circumstances didn't happen, even if one saying oh if I
can redeem it fine who cares you know now I'm seeing that
you're able to redeem an אשם asham and turn the money into
an עולה, olah, so I'll come to do it even without those
special circumstances, okay? Where I wouldn't make that mistake if it wasn't
the original. If it wasn't the original I know that you can
never redeem the original, okay? So therefore if there you allowed me
to redeem it, משום דגזר אחר כפרה אטו לפני כפרה. mishum degazar
achar kapara atu lifnei kapara. If you allow me to redeem the
original one after atonement, I'll come to redeem it even before atonement.
I'll say you can redeem an אשם. asham. אבל גבי תמורת אשם
וולד תמורתו, aval gabei tmuras asham ve'vlad tmuraso, but when it's not
the original animal, it's a תמורה tmura or child of a תמורה,
tmura, אימא מודי להו לרבנן, eima modi lehu lerabbanan, maybe there he
agrees, nobody will ever make any mistakes, so there you can redeem
it, let it graze and redeem it, no problem. ואי אשמיעינן התם,
ve'i ashmi'inan hatam, had he said there let it die, בהך קאמרי
רבנן, behach ka'amri rabbanan, fine I would say there the rabbis I
there only there the rabbis say that you redeem it, אבל גבי
אשם aval gabei asham by the original one, מודו ליה לרבי אליעזר,
modu lei le-Rabbi Eliezer, maybe there they would be concerned that if
we let you redeem the original one, you'll come to redeeming even
without those special circumstances. צריכא, Tzericha, you need both cases. So here
the Gemara basically completely frames Rabbi Eliezer's reason of letting it die,
not as a fundamental identification of אשם asham with חטאת, chatas, but
because of a concern that if we let you redeem it, you
will come to accidentally redeem it even without special circumstances. And therefore
we'd better say totally off-limits, die, so you don't think that you
can redeem the אשם asham under non-special circumstances. I know, Rivka, I
appreciate your restraint. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה, Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah, says Rav Nachman, says Rabbah, זו מחלוקת לאחר כפרה. zu machlokes
le-achar kaparah. אבל לפני כפרה, Aval lifnei kaparah, דברי הכל הוא עצמו
יקרב שלמים. divrei hakol hu atzmo yikarev shelamim. So the whole debate
in the Mishnah is that, is before the atonement happened. But after
atonement, everybody says, oh, I'm sorry, excuse me, no, after the atonement,
wait just one second, let me just double-check Rashi one second. Right,
so the issue here about what's the story about a ולד חטאת,
vlad chatas, what do you do with a child or תמורת אשם,
tmuras asham, a ולד אשם vlad asham or תמורת אשם, tmuras asham,
the child or the תמורה, tmura, whether it's this type of an
עולה, olah, that type of an עולה, olah, die? He says that
it's only after you've already used your original אשם. asham. You've already
used your original אשם, asham, what now do you do with the
תמורה, tmura, the ולד, vlad, or whatever? אבל לפני כפרה, Aval lifnei
kaparah, if you haven't used your original one, דברי הכל הוא עצמו
יקרב אשם. divrei hakol hu atzmo yikarev asham. You can even bring
this thing itself as an אשם, asham, which is a very shocking
statement because we normally understand תמורת אשם, tmuras asham, תמורת חטאת, tmuras
chatas, you have to let it die, תמורת אשם tmuras asham you
let it graze, and here he's saying that no, that's only if
the original was already being used. But if you didn't use the
original and you have here the תמורה, tmura, you can go ahead
and use the תמורה tmura itself as the אשם. asham. אמר רבא
שתי תשובות בדבר. Amar Rava shtei teshuvos badavar. Rava does not like
that. Two responses. חדא דאין אדם מתכפר בדבר הבא בעבירה. Chada de-ein
adam miskaper bedavar haba ba-aveira. Number one is you cannot use a
תמורת אשם tmuras asham for your אשם asham because that came through
sin. Now I have to stop for a minute and say, this
is why before we learned this perek, you know, most of us
probably would have thought that when the Torah says a תמורה tmura
becomes קדוש, kadosh, that it doesn't mean that you can bring it
as a קרבן, korban, right? Maybe you have to redeem it or
whatever, at least we could have thought that's possible. I mean, you
just did this sin and now you're going to bring this as
a קרבן. korban. So actually, while that's not true by an עולה
olah and שלמים shelamim and sort of other types of קרבנות, korbanos,
if the whole point of the קרבן korban is to atone for
sin, we're not going to allow that the thing that is coming
to atone for sin was itself a product of sin. So therefore
Rava says, to suggest we're going to use a תמורת אשם tmuras
asham as an אשם, asham, even if you haven't used the first
one, it's inconceivable. Number one, it's a product of a sin. ועוד
התני רבי חנינא לסיועי לרבי יהושע בן לוי דאמר ולד ראשון קרב
ולד שני אינו קרב. Ve-od hatani Rabbi Chanina lesiyu'ei le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi de-amar vlad rishon karev vlad sheni eino karev. We had talked
before, right, that the first child could be brought by a שלמים,
shelamim, not the second child. Why is that relevant here? Because here
one of the cases in the Mishnah is the child of a
תמורה, tmura, and that's two degrees removed. We had said way before,
although only according to some opinions, but okay, that two degrees removed
cannot be brought as a קרבן. korban. So how can you say
here the ולד vlad of a תמורה tmura can be brought as
an אשם asham if you still don't have, if you haven't yet
used the original one? I would add to all of this, which
interestingly the Gemara is not saying, is we have a very general
principle that anything by a חטאת chatas dies, by an אשם asham
has to let graze, and one of the classic cases is תמורה
tmura and a ולד. vlad. So how could we think in those
cases? But anyway, here the Gemara is thinking maybe if you haven't
yet been atoned and you can use this for your אשם, asham,
that actually you can use that for your אשם. asham. And Rava
completely rejects that. So the Gemara says, we'll do just one more
line, אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ela i itmar hachi itmar, if
it was said, here's how it was said. אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה מחלוקת קודם כפרה. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha machlokes kodem kaparah. The question, what do you do with this
אשם, asham, die, this type of an עולה, olah, that type of
an עולה, olah, if it's a תמורה tmura or ולד, vlad, is
only before the owners have actually got, you know, used their first
אשם asham and got their atonement. אבל לאחר כפרה הוא עצמו קרב
עולה. Aval le-achar kaparah hu atzmo karev olah. Ah, after the owners
have gotten their atonement, now he says, why not just use the
thing itself for an עולה? olah? Meaning, right, what do you normally
say by an אשם? asham? Let it graze, take the money, use
the money and buy an עולה, olah, right? So he says, well,
why not just use the אשם asham itself? As long as the
money is going towards an עולה, olah, use the אשם asham itself
as an עולה. olah. So while the first אשם asham is still
around, you could say, you know, there you're still under the context
of an אשם, asham, so this can't completely transform its identity. But
after your first אשם asham was brought and you're no longer under
the context of an אשם asham and you're no longer obligated for
an אשם, asham, this thing which has to graze and get a
blemish and the money goes for an עולה, olah, let it just
automatically use it directly for an עולה, olah, at least assuming it's
a male. Okay, and now the Gemara, we'll just read one more
line, והתני רבי חנינא לסיועי לרבי יהושע בן לוי, ve-hatani Rabbi Chanina
lesiyu'ei le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, how can you say that if it's
a child of a תמורה, tmura, that's two degrees removed, and you're
not supposed to use two... degrees removed as a קרבן, korban, at
least according to one opinion? The גמרא Gemara says קשיא, kasha, that
remains a question. So interestingly here, we raise, we have said before
that once a אשם asham is put out to graze, if you
שחט shecht it, it becomes an עולה, ola, because that's where it's
headed. Here he's trying to claim that even we that he tries
to claim again, these are things we never say, normally this is
this completely breaks all of our normal rules, but he's basically trying
to say, once you already have used your first אשם, asham, if
this is now this one is grazing and heading for an עולה,
ola, for an עולה ola you can straight away bring it as
an עולה ola because that's where it is heading once you have
already brought your first אשם asham and that's no longer part of
your